<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/abel/Downloads/grobid-0.5.6/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd" xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">A case report of neonatal COVID-19 infection in China</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher />
				<availability status="unknown"><licence /></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Shaoshuai</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology</orgName>
								<orgName key="instit1" type="institution">Tongji Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName key="instit2" type="institution">Tongji Medical College</orgName>
								<orgName key="instit3" type="institution">Huazhong University of Science and Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Wuhan</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Lili</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology</orgName>
								<orgName key="instit1" type="institution">Tongji Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName key="instit2" type="institution">Tongji Medical College</orgName>
								<orgName key="instit3" type="institution">Huazhong University of Science and Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Wuhan</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ling</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Pediatrics</orgName>
								<orgName key="instit1" type="institution">Tongji Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName key="instit2" type="institution">Tongji Medical College</orgName>
								<orgName key="instit3" type="institution">Huazhong University of Science and Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Wuhan</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Weiyong</forename><surname>Liu</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Laboratory Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName key="instit1" type="institution">Tongji Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName key="instit2" type="institution">Tongji Medical College</orgName>
								<orgName key="instit3" type="institution">Huazhong University of Science and Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Wuhan</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Yong</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Infectious Disease</orgName>
								<orgName key="instit1" type="institution">Tongji Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName key="instit2" type="institution">Tongji Medical College</orgName>
								<orgName key="instit3" type="institution">Huazhong University of Science and Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Wuhan</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jingyi</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology</orgName>
								<orgName key="instit1" type="institution">Tongji Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName key="instit2" type="institution">Tongji Medical College</orgName>
								<orgName key="instit3" type="institution">Huazhong University of Science and Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Wuhan</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ling</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology</orgName>
								<orgName key="instit1" type="institution">Tongji Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName key="instit2" type="institution">Tongji Medical College</orgName>
								<orgName key="instit3" type="institution">Huazhong University of Science and Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Wuhan</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Ling</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">A case report of neonatal COVID-19 infection in China</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date />
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1093/cid/ciaa225/5803274</idno>
					<note>*JZ and LF contributed equally Correspondence: Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/cid/advance-article-abstract/doi/10.1093/cid/ciaa225/5803274 by Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul user on 16 March 2020 Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/cid/advance-article-abstract/doi/10.1093/cid/ciaa225/5803274 by Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul user on 16 March 2020</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>

		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="GROBID" version="0.5.6" when="2020-03-16T22:29+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div><p>In December 2019, the 2019 novel coronavirus disease (COVID-19) caused by SARS-CoV-2 emerged in China and now has spread in many countries. Pregnant women are susceptible population of COVID-19 which are more likely to have complications and even progresse to severe illness. We report a case of neonatal COVID-19 infection in China with pharyngeal swabs tested positive by rRT-PCR assay 36 hours after birth. However, whether the case is a vertical transmission from mother to child remains to be confirmed.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div><head>Background</head><p>In December 2019, a pneumonia caused by 2019 novel coronavirus (SARS-CoV-2) emerged in Wuhan, Hubei Province. Since COVID-19 is highly contagious with a certain mortality rate, it was classified as a class B infectious disease and was managed as a Class A infectious disease in China in January 2020 </p><p>We report a case of neonatal COVID-19 infection in China with pharyngeal swabs tested positive by rRT-PCR assay 36 hours after birth. However, whether the case is a vertical transmission from mother to child remains to be confirmed.</p></div>
<div><head>Case presentation</head><p>The mother of the neonatal patient is a 34-year-old pregnant woman who lives near the Huanan Seafood Wholesale Market (about 1.2km walking distance) in Wuhan. She has not been to the market during pregnancy and her family has no confirmed or suspected cases of COVID-19, but more than 15 people had been dignosed in the same community she lives in.</p><p>She has a history of hypothyroidism for 4 years and has been treated with oral drugs, with no history of hypertension, diabetes, or heart disease. She had a terminal of pregnancy due to chromosome abnormalities in 2016. She is allergic to penicillin and first-generation cephalosporin (positive in skin test). At 20:00 on February 1, 2020, the 40-week gestation pregnant woman developed small amount of per vaginal bleeding and lower abdominal pain. Two hours later, she developed a fever (37.8 &#8451;) and attended to Wuhan women and children medical care center for medical advice. As she was febrile, she was referred to the fever clinic of Wuhan Tongji Hospital the next morning. Thoracic computerized tomography scan showed ground-glass opacities in the left upper and lower lobes, indicating the possibility of viral pneumonia </p><p>Half an hour after birth, the infant vomitted once after feeding formula, which we considered to be swallowing syndrome. After gastric lavage, the infant could be fed normally.</p><p>Blood tests of the neonate revealed lymphopenia (2.43&#215;10 9 /L, normal: 3-8&#215;10 9 /L), deranged liver function tests (AST 143U/L , normal: &#8804;41 U/L. TBIL 33.0 umol/L, normal: &#8804;26 umol/L. IBIL 26.0 umol/L, normal: &#8804;16.8 umol/L.) and elevated creatine kinase level (479 U/L , normal: &#8804;41 U/L). Intravenous penicillin G (15wu q.d, intravenous bolus) and vitamin K1 (1mg q.d, intravenously) were given as antibiotic prophylaxis and to prevent coagulopathy, respectively.</p><p>The mother was well and afebrile during the immediate post-operative period. She had no cough or any other discomfort such as diarrhea, nausea and vomiting. Her vital signs were stable with blood oxygen saturation of 99%. Antiviral treatment including 40 &#956;g of recombinant human interferon &#945;1b atomized inhalation with 2 mL of sterilization injection water was used twice a day, and ganciclovir (0&#183;25 g every 12 h, intravenously). Abipenem (0.3g every 12 h, intravenously) and moxifloxacin (0.4g q.d, intravenously) were used for anti-infection. The mother had intermittent fever on the first postoperative day with the highest temperature up to 38.3 &#176; C. She was given methylprednisolone(20mg intravenously ). Her pharyngeal swab sampled for SARS-CoV-2 reported back as positive later that day.</p><p>Pharyngeal swab specimen was collected immediately from the infant (36 hours after birth), along with the breast milk of the mother. We recommended the mother not to breastfeed and empty the breast milk to avoid mastitis.</p><p>The mental response of the newborn was acceptable the first day after birth and his blood oxygen saturation maintained above 92% without supplyment of oxygen. On February 4, the second day after the surgery, the mother's vitals were stable and she was given methylprednisolone(40mg q.d, intravenously). The neonate was well and his blood gas analysis showed: PH 7. On February 5, the newborn's vital signs were stable with the blood oxygen saturation maintained above 90%, with no discomfort such as apnea or vomiting. The result of pharyngeal swab for SARS-CoV-2 was positive at 36 hours after birth. Combining all the laboratory results with fully discussion, we made a diagnosis that the infant was confirmed with SARS-CoV-2 infection. Since the neonatal department of Tongji Hospital did not have the isolation conditions for the diagnosed newborn, he was transferred to Wuhan Children's Hospital for further isolation later that day. After finding evidence of neonatal infection, we performed nucleic acid tests for SARS-CoV-2 on cord blood and placenta specimens that we retained during the operation, and the results were negative. The mother's breast milk sample was negative for SARS-CoV-2 as well. We followed up the newborn's condition after he was transferred to Wuhan Children's Hospital. He was well and afebrile with no cough or vomiting. He was closely monitored in isolation and no special treatment was given. Chest CT on Feb 6 showed high-density nodular shadow under the pleura of the posterior segment of the upper lobe of the right lung.</p><p>Chest CT on Feb 12 showed that the upper lobe and lower lobe of the right lung were scattered with small pieces of patchy shadow. Chest CT on Feb 17 showed that a few small pieces of patchy shadow in the upper lobe of the right lung, which were absorbed compared with the previous one. On </p></div>
<div><head>Discussion</head><p>The severity of viral pneumonia in pregnancy is evidently related to physiological and immunological changes that result in a shift from cell-mediated to humoral-mediated immunity </p><p>shows that SARS during pregnancy is associated with high incidences of spontaneous miscarriage, preterm delivery, and intrauterine growth restriction </p><p>There have been several studies concerning intrauterine vertical transmission potential of COVID-19 and its effects on newborns </p><p>We report the first case of neonatal COVID-19 infection in China whose mother was confirmed with COVID-19. The clinical manifestations of the mother and the baby were both mild and the baby's prognosis was well. Whether the case is intrauterine vertical transmission or not remains controversial. Although the results of nucleic acid detection of cord blood and placenta in this case are negative, which do not support the diagnosis of intrauterine transmission, but the possibility of vertical intrauterine transmission of SARS-CoV-2 is not ruled out. The reasons are as follows: 1) When the viral load is not high enough, the detection rate of existing methods is limited and false negatives may occur. Therefore, the negative results of umbilical cord blood and placental nucleic acid during the operation do not exclude the possibility of false negatives. 2) According to the clinical manifestations, the pregnant woman first had fever symptoms at 22:00 on February 1. However, the CT result after a few hours showed ground-glass opacities in the left upper and lower lobes, suggesting that the pregnant woman may have been asymptomatic in the early stage. Since we lack the data of maternal viral load, there is no evidence whether the fetus has been infected with maternal viremia in utero before the mother had any clinical manifestation.3) In addition to this case, neonatal infections have been reported in other provinces and cities in China </p><p>We also discussed whether the newborn is a nosocomial infection. According to the</p></div>
<div><head>No.225-Management Guidelines for Obstetric Patients and Neonates Born to Mothers With</head><p>Suspected or Probable Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome (SARS) </p><p>The newborn had early clamping of the umbilical cord and early cleansing to remove maternal blood and amniotic fluid. Then he was transferred to an isolation room in the neonatal nursery shortly after delivery. The mother wore a N95 mask during the operation and had no close contact with the newborn. However, since we did not retain the specimens of the newborn's pharyngeal swabs shortly after birth, the first time we took samples of the newborn's pharyngeal swabs was 36 hours after birth. During this period, we can not rule out the possibility of other contact transmission of newborn. In addition, it has been confirmed that SARS coronavirus was detected by RT-PCR in the maternal peritoneal fluid collected during cesarean section in 28 SARS patients </p></div>
<div><head>Conclusion</head><p>Clinical datas on COVID-19 infection in newborns are still very limited. Whether SARS-CoV-2 can transmit vertically through placenta and its short-term and long-term harm to offsprings is still unclear. Therefore, it is important to keep all the specimens of SARS-CoV-2 infected and suspected pregnant women and their newborns, including pharyngeal swabs, peripheral blood, placenta tissue after delivery, amniotic fluid, cord blood, newborn pharyngeal swabs and breast milk, for in-depth study and continuous follow-up observation of future generations.  </p></div><note place="foot">Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/cid/advance-article-abstract/doi/10.1093/cid/ciaa225/5803274 by Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul user on 16 March 2020</note>
		<figDesc>476&#8593;&#65292;PCO2 28.2 mmHg&#8595;&#65292; PO2 116.0 mmHg&#8593;&#65292;HCO3-20.6 mmol/L&#8595;&#65292;BE -1.30 mmol/L&#65292;SPO2 98.4%. A complete set of pediatric viruses results of the infant reported back as negative (including CMV, RV, TOX, HSV I, HSV II, ECHO, PVB19, EBV, CA16, CVB, MV, VZV). The neonatal chest x-ray showed thickened lung texture with no abnormalities in heart and palate (fig.2). The infant was given formula 25ml every 3 hours and he was closely monitored.</figDesc><figDesc>Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/cid/advance-article-abstract/doi/10.1093/cid/ciaa225/5803274 by Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul user on 16 March 2020</figDesc><figDesc>Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/cid/advance-article-abstract/doi/10.1093/cid/ciaa225/5803274 by Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul user on 16 March 2020</figDesc><figDesc>Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/cid/advance-article-abstract/doi/10.1093/cid/ciaa225/5803274 by Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul user on 16 March 2020 Figures: Chest CT obtained on February 2, 2020. Chest CT showed signs of infection in the left upper and lower lobe, indicating the possibility of viral pneumonia, with limited emphysema in the right lower lobe and a little cord focus in the right middle lobe.</figDesc><figDesc>Chest x-ray of the newborn obtained on February 4, 2020. Chest x-ray showed</figDesc><figDesc>Downloaded from https://academic.oup.com/cid/advance-article-abstract/doi/10.1093/cid/ciaa225/5803274 by Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul user on 16 March 2020</figDesc><figDesc>The laboratory results of the infant reported back as negative including legionella pneumophila, chlamydia pneumoniae, mycoplasma pneumoniae, Q fever rickettsia, adenovirus, respiratory syncytial virus, influenza A virus, influenza B virus, parainfluenza virus 1 / 2 / 3.</figDesc></body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div><head>Declaration of interests</head><p>We declare no competing interests. </p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Emerging understandings of 2019-nCoV</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Lancet</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint />
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title />
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S0140-</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A novel coronavirus associated with severe acute respiratory syndrome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Ksiazek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Erdman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Goldsmith</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint />
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title />
		<idno type="DOI">10.1056/NEJMoa030781</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">348</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">20</biblScope>
			<biblScope from="1953" to="1966" unit="page" />
			<date type="published" when="2003" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title />
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Zaki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Van Boheemen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Bestebroer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint />
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title />
		<idno type="DOI">10.1056/NEJMoa1211721</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">367</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">19</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">World Health Organization. Summary of probable SARS cases with onset of illness from 1</title>
		<idno>EB/OL]. (2004-04</idno>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2002-11-31" />
			<biblScope from="2020" to="2021" unit="page" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">World Health Organization. Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV)</title>
		<imprint />
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pneumonia in pregnancy</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Ramsey</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Ramin</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Obstet Gynecol Clin N Am</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope from="553" to="69" unit="page" />
			<date type="published" when="2001" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">A case-controlled study comparing clinical course and outcomes of pregnant and non-pregnant women with severe acute respiratory syndrome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Leung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint />
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BJOG</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope from="771" to="775" unit="page" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Pregnancy and perinatal outcomes of women with severe acute respiratory syndrome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Chow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Leung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint />
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title />
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ajog.2003.11.019</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Obstet Gynecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">191</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope from="292" to="297" unit="page" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Pneumonia and pregnancy outcomes: a nationwide population-based study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Keller</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint />
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title />
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.ajog.2012.08.023</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Obstet Gynecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">207</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title />
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Takahashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Kitajima</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Kusuda</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Morioka</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Itabashi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Pandemic</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title />
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Japan</forename><surname>Neonates</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Emerg Infect Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">17</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope from="1763" to="1768" unit="page" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title />
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/cid/ciaa225/5803274byUniversidadeFederaldoRioGrandedoSuluseron16</idno>
		<ptr target="https://academic.oup.com/cid/advance-article-abstract/doi/10.1093/cid/ciaa225/5803274byUniversidadeFederaldoRioGrandedoSuluseron16" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinical characteristics and intrauterine vertical transmission potential of 2019-nCoV infection in nine pregnant women: a retrospective review of medical records</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020-02-12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published online</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinical analysis of 10 neonates born to mothers with 2019-nCoV pneumonia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transl Pediatr</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020-02-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published online</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title />
		<idno type="DOI">10.21037/tp.2020.02.06</idno>
		<ptr target="http://dx.doi.org/10.21037/tp.2020.02.06" />
		<imprint />
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">National Health Commission of the People's Republic of China</title>
		<ptr target="http://www.nhc.gov.cn/xcs/s3574/202002/5bc099fc9144445297e8776838e57ddc.shtml" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Transcript of Press Conference on Feb</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020-02-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">225-Management Guidelines for Obstetric Patients and Neonates Born to Mothers With Suspected or Probable Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome (SARS)</title>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.jogc.2017.04.024</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Obstet Gynaecol Can</title>
		<editor>Maxwell C&#65292;McGeer A&#65292;Tai KFY&#65292;Sermer M</editor>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">39</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope from="130" to="137" unit="page" />
			<date type="published" when="2017-08" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Impact of Middle East Respiratory Syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV) on pregnancy andperinatal outcome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Alserehi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Wali</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Alshukairi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Alraddadi</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1186/s12879-016-1437-y</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BMC Infect Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">16</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">105</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2016-03-02" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Infants born to mothers with severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Shek</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Ng</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Gpg</forename><surname>Fung</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pediatrics</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">112</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">254</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2003-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title />
		<idno type="DOI">10.1093/cid/ciaa225/5803274byUniversidadeFederaldoRioGrandedoSuluseron16</idno>
		<ptr target="https://academic.oup.com/cid/advance-article-abstract/doi/10.1093/cid/ciaa225/5803274byUniversidadeFederaldoRioGrandedoSuluseron16" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020-03" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>