<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/abel/Downloads/grobid-0.5.6/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd" xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Defining the Epidemiology of Covid-19 -Studies Needed</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher />
				<availability status="unknown"><licence /></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Marc</forename><surname>Lipsitch</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Phil</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">David</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Swerdlow</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Dr</roleName><forename type="first">Lyn</forename><surname>Finelli</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Defining the Epidemiology of Covid-19 -Studies Needed</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date />
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1056/NEJMp2002125</idno>
					<note>Perspective The NEW ENGLA ND JOURNAL of MEDICINE Defining the Epidemiology of Covid-19 The New England Journal of Medicine Downloaded from nejm.org at UFRGS on March 16, 2020. For personal use only. No other uses without permission.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>

		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="GROBID" version="0.5.6" when="2020-03-16T22:29+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>		<profileDesc>
			<abstract />
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div><p>T he epidemic of 2019 novel coronavirus (now called SARS-CoV-2, causing the disease Covid-19) has expanded from Wuhan throughout China and is being exported to a growing number of countries, some of which have seen onward transmission. Early efforts have focused on describing the clinical course, counting severe cases, and treating the sick. Experience with the Middle East respiratory syndrome (MERS), pandemic influenza, and other outbreaks has shown that as an epidemic evolves, we face an urgent need to expand public health activities in order to elucidate the epidemiology of the novel virus and characterize its potential impact. The impact of an epidemic depends on the number of persons infected, the infection's transmissibility, and the spectrum of clinical severity.</p><p>Thus, several questions are especially critical. First, what is the full spectrum of disease severity (which can range from asymp-tomatic, to symptomatic-but-mild, to severe, to requiring hospitalization, to fatal)?</p><p>Second, how transmissible is the virus?</p><p>Third, who are the infectors -how do the infected person's age, the severity of illness, and other characteristics of a case affect the risk of transmitting the infection to others? Of vital interest is the role that asymptomatic or presymptomatic infected persons play in transmission. When and for how long is the virus present in respiratory secretions?</p><p>And fourth, what are the risk factors for severe illness or death? And how can we identify groups most likely to have poor outcomes so that we can focus prevention and treatment efforts?</p><p>The table lists approaches to answering these questions, each of which has shown success in prior disease outbreaks, especially MERS and pandemic H1N1 influenza. </p><p>More generally, it is useful to synthesize data from simultaneous surveillance studies, epidemiologic field investigations, and case series. </p><p>A key point of these recommendations is that viral testing should not be used only for clinical care. A proportion of testing capacity must be reserved to support public health efforts to characterize the trajectory and severity of the disease. Although this approach may result in many negative test results and therefore appear "wasteful," such setaside capacity will permit a far clearer understanding of the spread of the epidemic and wiser use of resources to combat it. Testing in unexplained clusters or severe cases of acute respiratory infections, regardless of a patient's travel history, may be a sensitive way to screen for chains of transmission that may have been missed. Such findings are relevant particularly in light of evidence that even Singapore, with one of the world's best public health systems, has found Early investments in characterizing SARS-CoV-2 will pay off handsomely in improving the epidemic response. If sustained transmission takes off outside China, as many experts expect, the urgency of the epidemic will necessitate choices about which interventions to employ, under which circumstances, and for how long. Starting these epidemiologic and surveillance activities promptly will enable us to choose the most efficient ways of controlling the epidemic and help us avoid interventions that may be unnecessarily costly or unduly restrictive of normal activity.</p><p>Many urban centers in China are or will soon be overwhelmed with the treatment of severe cases.</p><p>It may be difficult for many of them to perform the kinds of studies described here. One exception is systematic surveys of persons who are not suspected to have Covid-19 or who have mild respiratory illness, to assess whether they are currently subclinically infected (viral testing), have been infected previously (serologic testing), or both. These studies, which will inform estimates of the severity spectrum, will be most informative in the settings that have the most cases.</p><p>Fortunately, the numbers of detected cases outside China remain manageable for public health authorities -and too small for the conduct of such studies. But it is vital for jurisdictions outside mainland China to prepare to perform these studies as case numbers grow. Disclosure forms provided by the authors are available at NEJM.org. This article was published on February 19, 2020, at NEJM.org.</p></div><figDesc>Types of Evidence Needed for Controlling an Epidemic.</figDesc></body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div><head>PERSPECTIVE PERSPECTIVE</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Improving the evidence base for decision making during a pandemic: the example of 2009 influenza A/ H1N1</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lipsitch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Finelli</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Heffernan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Leung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Redd</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Biosecur Bioterror</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope from="89" to="115" unit="page" />
			<date type="published" when="2011" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Potential Biases in Estimating Absolute and Relative Case-Fatality Risks during Outbreaks</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lipsitch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Donnelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fraser</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS Negl Trop Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">9</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">3846</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2015" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">How to maintain surveillance for novel influenza A H1N1 when there are too many cases to count</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Lipsitch</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Hayden</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Cowling</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Leung</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">374</biblScope>
			<biblScope from="1209" to="1220" unit="page" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Influenza-like illness in a community surrounding a school-based outbreak of 2009 pandemic influenza A (H1N1) virus -Chicago</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Janusz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">E</forename><surname>Cortes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><surname>Serdarevic</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Infect Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">52</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Suppl 1: S94-S101</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Household transmission of 2009 pandemic influenza A (H1N1) virus in the United</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Cauchemez</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Donnelly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Reed</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint />
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>