<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/abel/Downloads/grobid-0.5.6/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd" xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Clinical Findings in 111 Cases of Influenza A (H7N9) Virus Infection The Beijing Acute Kidney Injury Trial (BAKIT) workgroup. Fluid balance and mortality in critically ill patients with acute kidney injury: a multicenter prospective epidemiological stu View project pneumonia View project Clinical Findings in 111 Cases of Influenza A (H7N9) Virus Infection A BS T R AC T background</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher />
				<availability status="unknown"><licence /></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2014-05">May 2014.</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wang</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Jiang</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Zhu</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wen</forename><forename type="middle">Y</forename></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Xi</forename><surname>Xm</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Bin</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Xiuming</forename><surname>Xi</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Wei</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Hai-Nv</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Hong-Zhou</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Bin Du, M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Hong</forename><surname>Shang</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Jian-He</forename><surname>Gan</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Shui-Hua</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Yi-Da</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Fang, M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Yin-Zhong</forename><surname>Shen</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Xiu-Ming</forename><surname>Xi</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Qin</forename><surname>Gu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Xian-Mei</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Hong-Ping</forename><surname>Qu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Zheng</forename><surname>Yan</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Fang-</roleName><forename type="first">Ming</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Wei</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Zhan-Cheng</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Guang-Fa</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Ling-Xiang</forename><surname>Ruan</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Wei-Hong</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Jun</forename><surname>Ye</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Hui-Fang</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Xing-Wang</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Wen-Hong</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Xu-Chen</forename><surname>Fang</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>He, M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Wei-Feng</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Juan</forename><surname>Xie</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Mei</forename><surname>Zeng</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Xian-Zheng</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Jun</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Qi</forename><surname>Xia</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Zhao-Chen</forename><surname>Jin</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Qi</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Chao</forename><surname>Tang</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Zhi-Yong</forename><surname>Zhang</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Bao-Min</forename><surname>Hou</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Zhi-Xian</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Ji-Fang</forename><surname>Sheng</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Nan-Shan</forename><surname>Zhong</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>M.D</roleName><forename type="first">Lan-Juan</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Dr</roleName><forename type="first">Lan-Juan</forename></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Nan-Shan</forename><surname>Zhong</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Drs</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">-N</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><roleName>Cao, Du, Shang</roleName><forename type="first">H.-Z</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">J.-H</forename><surname>Gan</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">S.-H</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Li at the State Key Laboratory for Diagnosis and Treatment of Infectious Diseases, First Affiliated Hospital, Col-lege of Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName key="instit1" type="institution">China-Japan Friendship Hospital &amp; Capital Medical University</orgName>
								<orgName key="instit2" type="institution">Capital Medical University</orgName>
								<orgName key="instit3" type="institution">USDA, ARS</orgName>
								<orgName key="instit4" type="institution">USHRL</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Fort Pierce, Florida</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">at the Guangzhou Insti-tute of Respiratory Disease, State Key Laboratory of Respiratory Diseases</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Zhejiang University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>79 Qingchun Rd</addrLine>
									<postCode>310003</postCode>
									<settlement>Hangzhou City</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName key="instit1" type="institution">First Affiliated Hospital</orgName>
								<orgName key="instit2" type="institution">Guangzhou Medical University</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>151 Yanjiang Rd</addrLine>
									<postCode>510120</postCode>
									<settlement>Guangzhou City</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Clinical Findings in 111 Cases of Influenza A (H7N9) Virus Infection The Beijing Acute Kidney Injury Trial (BAKIT) workgroup. Fluid balance and mortality in critically ill patients with acute kidney injury: a multicenter prospective epidemiological stu View project pneumonia View project Clinical Findings in 111 Cases of Influenza A (H7N9) Virus Infection A BS T R AC T background</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2014-05">May 2014.</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1056/NEJMoa1305584</idno>
					<note type="submission">Article in New England Journal of Medicine &#183; May 2013</note>
					<note>See discussions, stats, and author profiles for this publication at: https://www.researchgate.net/publication/236931444 42 authors, including: Some of the authors of this publication are also working on these related projects: 278 PUBLICATIONS 6,952 CITATIONS SEE PROFILE Bin Du Peking Union Medical College Hospital 211 PUBLICATIONS 3,850 CITATIONS SEE PROFILE 111 PUBLICATIONS 1,280 CITATIONS SEE PROFILE 132 PUBLICATIONS 3,650 CITATIONS SEE PROFILE All content following this page was uploaded by Bin Cao on 28 The user has requested enhancement of the downloaded file. T h e n e w e ng l a n d j o u r na l o f m e dic i n e n engl j med nejm.org 1 original article The authors' affiliations are listed in the Appendix. Address reprint requests to contributed equal-ly to this article. This article was published on May 22, 2013, at NEJM.org. N Engl J Med 2013.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>

		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="GROBID" version="0.5.6" when="2020-03-16T22:29+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div><head>background</head><p>During the spring of 2013, a novel avian-origin influenza A (H7N9) virus emerged and spread among humans in China. Data were lacking on the clinical characteristics of the infections caused by this virus.</p></div>
<div><head>methods</head><p>Using medical charts, we collected data on 111 patients with laboratory-confirmed avian-origin influenza A (H7N9) infection through May 10, 2013.</p></div>
<div><head>results</head><p>Of the 111 patients we studied, 76.6% were admitted to an intensive care unit (ICU), and 27.0% died. The median age was 61 years, and 42.3% were 65 years of age or older; 31.5% were female. A total of 61.3% of the patients had at least one underlying medical condition. Fever and cough were the most common presenting symptoms. On admission, 108 patients (97.3%) had findings consistent with pneumonia. Bilateral ground-glass opacities and consolidation were the typical radiologic findings. Lymphocytopenia was observed in 88.3% of patients, and thrombo cytopenia in 73.0%. Treatment with antiviral drugs was initiated in 108 patients (97.3%) at a median of 7 days after the onset of illness. The median times from the onset of illness and from the initiation of antiviral therapy to a negative viral test result on real-time reverse-transcriptase-polymerase-chain-reaction assay were 11 days (interquartile range, 9 to 16) and 6 days (interquartile range, 4 to 7), respectively. Multivariate analysis revealed that the presence of a coexisting medical condition was the only independent risk factor for the acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) (odds ratio, 3.42; 95% confidence interval, 1.21 to 9.70; P = 0.02). conclusions During the evaluation period, the novel H7N9 virus caused severe illness, including pneumonia and ARDS, with high rates of ICU admission and death. (Funded by the National Natural Science Foundation of China and others.) The New England Journal of Medicine Downloaded from nejm.org on May 22, 2013. For personal use only. No other uses without permission.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div><p>2 O n March 30, 2013, three patients with fatal cases of rapid, progressive pneumonia were confirmed to be infected with a novel avian-origin influenza A (H7N9) virus that had not been detected in humans and animals previously. </p><p>Global attention was soon focused on the situation because of the increasing number of new cases and the high rate of death associated with these infections. </p></div>
<div><head>Me thods</head></div>
<div><head>Data Sources</head><p>We conducted a retrospective study focusing on the clinical characteristics of confirmed cases of the novel H7N9 virus infection. The strategy of new case identification in Beijing was different from that used in other areas in China. In Beijing, all patients with fever and influenza-like illness or pneumonia who had been visiting Shanghai, Zhejiang, or Jiangsu or who had a history of poultry exposure within 2 weeks before the onset of illness were required to be screened for H7N9 virus. In other areas, only patients with fever and rapidly progressing pneumonia who had no response to antibiotic therapy were tested for H7N9 virus.</p><p>The case definitions of confirmed human infection with the novel H7N9 virus have been described by </p><p>The medical records of patients were copied and sent to the data-collection center in Beijing. A team of physicians who had been taking care of patients with H7N9 virus infection reviewed the data. Our data collection and analysis, which were independent and differed from those described by </p><p>We used a standardized case-report form to collect clinical data. All data were entered in duplicate into a computerized database. If information was not clear, the working group in Beijing contacted the clinician responsible for the care of the patient for clarification. Definitions of moderate-to-severe acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS), rhabdomyolysis, pneumonia, acute kidney injury, and exposure to live poultry are provided in the Supplementary Appendix.</p></div>
<div><head>Laboratory Confirmation</head><p>Laboratory confirmation of the novel H7N9 virus was performed with the use of the same protocols described previously by Gao et al. </p><p>Blood cultures were performed for patients presenting with chills and shivering. Sputum or endotracheal aspirates were sent for identification of possible causative bacteria or fungi. Urinary antigen tests for Legionella pneumophila and Streptococcus pneumoniae (Binax) were also performed on all samples.</p></div>
<div><head>Statistical Analysis</head><p>Continuous variables were summarized as either means and standard deviations or medians with interquartile ranges. For categorical variables, the percentages of patients in each category were calculated. We used an unpaired Student's t-test, chi-square test, or Fisher's exact test, as appropriate, to compare the clinical characteristics of subgroups of patients who had moderate-to-severe ARDS and those who did not. </p></div>
<div><head>R e sult s</head></div>
<div><head>Epidemiologic Characteristics</head><p>This report describes 111 patients with confirmed H7N9 virus infection as of May 10, 2013 ( </p><p>H7N9 virus infection was diagnosed by means of serologic analysis alone in only 1 patient, in Shanghai, with negative results on realtime RT-PCR assay and viral culture. In 2 patients, the diagnosis was confirmed on both real-time RT-PCR assay and serologic analysis. In another 20 patients, the diagnosis was confirmed on both real-time RT-PCR assay and viral culture. All the other diagnoses were confirmed only on realtime RT-PCR assay.</p><p>The median age of the patients was 61 years (range, 3 to 88); 42.3% of the patients were 65 years of age or older. Male patients predominated in number over female patients, with a sex ratio of approximately 2:1. A total of 61.3% of the patients had one or more coexisting medical conditions. Coronary heart disease, hypertension, diabetes, and chronic obstructive pulmonary disease were the most common coexisting conditions. Two patients were pregnant, one in the first trimester and the other in the second trimester. On the basis of data from 62 patients (55.9%) for whom a definite date of exposure to live poultry was available, we estimated that the incubation period was 5 days (interquartile range, 2 to 8) ( </p></div>
<div><head>Clinical Features and Laboratory Abnormalities</head><p>The clinical characteristics of the patients are shown in </p><p>Representative radiologic findings for one 68-year-old man with hypertension were followed from his admission to the hospital (on day 7 after the onset of symptoms) until discharge (day 42). Unilateral ground-glass opacities and partial consolidation were observed in the left lung on admission </p><p>Klebsiella pneumoniae was isolated from both blood and sputum samples in five patients and methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus from blood and sputum samples in one patient.</p><p>A single pathogen was isolated from sputum or endotracheal samples in 18 patients, including 12 with Acinetobacter baumannii, 2 with Burkholderia cepacia, 1 with Pseudomonas aeruginosa, 1 with Enterobacter aerogenes, 1 with K. oxytoca, and 1 with P. putida. Two pathogens -K. pneumoniae and A. baumannii -were isolated from sputum or endotracheal samples obtained from 5 patients. All the bacterial pathogens were identified at least 48 hours after admission to the hospital.</p></div>
<div><head>Treatment and Viral-Load Kinetics</head><p>A total of 108 patients (97.3%) were treated with antiviral drugs ( </p><p>Data with respect to viral-load kinetics were available for 41 patients who had received antiviral agents (oseltamivir at a daily dose of 150 to 300 mg in 38 patients and oseltamivir followed by peramivir at a daily dose of 600 mg in 3 patients). The median times from the onset of illness and from the initiation of antiviral therapy to a negative test result on daily real-time RT-PCR assay were 11 days (interquartile range, 9 to 16) and 6 days (interquartile range, 4 to 7), respectively.</p><p>Seventy-nine patients (71.2%) also received antibiotic therapy within 6 hours after admission. Commonly used antibiotics included fluoroquinolones (in 34 patients), piperacillin (in 28 patients), imipenem or meropenem (in 21 patients), cephalosporins (in 21 patients), azithromycin (in 7 patients), and vancomycin (in 6 patients). One patient was treated with caspofungin on admission.</p><p>Sixty-nine patients (62.2%) were treated with at least one glucocorticoid, with the administration of intravenous methylprednisolone (median dose, 80 mg per day; range, 40 to 320 mg per day) in 64 patients, intravenous dexamethasone (5 mg per day) in 5 patients, and intravenous hydrocortisone (range, 100 to 200 mg per day) in 2 patients.</p></div>
<div><head>Complications and Clinical Outcomes</head><p>Of the 111 patients we evaluated, 85 (76.6%) were admitted to an intensive care unit (ICU); of these patients, 54 were directly admitted to the ICU, and 31 were admitted during hospitalization. Moderate-to-severe ARDS was the most common complication (in 79 patients), followed by shock (in 29 patients), acute kidney injury (in 18 patients), and rhabdomyolysis (in 11 patients). The median time from the onset of illness to ARDS was 7 days (range, 1 to 19). The median time from the onset of illness to shock was 8 days (range, 3 to 55) </p><p>Univariate analysis showed that the risk factors for moderate-to-severe ARDS were an age of 65 years or older and the presence of at least one coexisting medical condition, a lymphocyte count of less than 1000 per cubic millimeter, an aspartate aminotransferase level of more than 40 U per liter, and a creatine kinase level of more than 200 U per liter; patients were less likely to have been treated with oseltamivir or peramivir within 3 days after the onset of illness </p><p>As of May 10, a total of 30 patients had died, 49 patients had been discharged from the hospital with full recovery, and 30 patients remained hospitalized; of the patients who were still in the hospital, 24 were in an ICU. One of the two pregnant patients had been discharged with full recovery, and the other remained hospitalized in 7 stable condition. Of the two patients who were not hospitalized, one died 7 days after symptom onset, and one had a full recovery. The median time from the onset of illness to death was 14 days (interquartile range, 8 to 24) </p></div>
<div><head>Discussion</head><p>The findings in this series of patients suggest that the novel H7N9 virus can cause severe illness, including pneumonia and ARDS, with 76.6% of patients who required admission to an ICU and 27.0% who died. It is possible that a larger number of patients have had infections that were not diagnosed because their symptoms were less severe.</p><p>Patients who were hospitalized with H7N9 virus infection had an uneven age distribution, with 42.3% who were 65 years of age or older. The age distribution was similar to that for seasonal influenza 6 but differed from the age distribution among patients who were hospitalized with H5N1 virus infection or those with pandemic H1N1 virus infection. In 2009, among 1461 Chinese patients who were hospitalized with pandemic H1N1 pneumonia, the mean age was 23 years (range, 27 days to 99 years). </p><p>The analysis of the initial patients infected with H7N9 virus revealed that antiviral therapy was initiated at a median of 7 days (range, 1 to 23) after the onset of illness, and patients with moderate-to-severe ARDS were less likely to have been treated within 5 days. WHO guidelines recommend the early initiation of antiviral therapy for patients who are infected with H5N1 virus or pandemic H1N1 virus, guidelines that we believe should be followed for patients infected with H7N9 virus. </p></div><note place="foot">n engl j med nejm.org</note>
		<figDesc>and Fig. S2 in the Supplementary Appendix).</figDesc><figDesc>Computed Tomographic Scans of the Chest in a 68-Year-Old Man with Pneumonia Caused by Avian Influenza A (H7N9) Virus.On day 7 after the onset of illness, at the time of hospital admission (Panel A), unilateral ground-glass opacities and partial consolidation were observed in the upper and lower portions of the left lung at the tracheal carina level. On day 9 (Panel B), there was rapid progression of the ground-glass opacities, which were observed in the posterior segment of the right lower lobe (not shown), along with consolidation in the left lung. On day 16 (Panel C), there were increased ground-glass opacities in the left lung and increased consolidation in both lungs. On day 42 (Panel D), when the patient was discharged from the hospital, ground-glass opacities and consolidation in both lungs had begun to resolve, with predominant reticular changes and distortion of the previously involved areas of parenchyma. Scans showing areas below the carina level, obtained on days7, 9, 16, and 42, are provided inFigure S3in the Supplementary Appendix.The New England Journal of Medicine Downloaded from nejm.org on May 22, 2013. For personal use only. No other uses without permission. Copyright &#169; 2013 Massachusetts Medical Society. All rights reserved.</figDesc><figDesc>Demographic and Epidemiologic Characteristics of 111 Patients Infected with H7N9 Virus in China. Cancers included breast cancer, colorectal cancer, thyroid cancer, thymoma, and lymphoma. Of these cancers, only one case of lymphoma was active, whereas the other cases were stable disease. &#8225; Hepatitis B infection was defined as a positive assay for hepatitis B surface antigen, with or without an elevated level of alanine aminotransferase. Downloaded from nejm.org on May 22, 2013. For personal use only. No other uses without permission. Copyright &#169; 2013 Massachusetts Medical Society. All rights reserved.</figDesc><figDesc>Clinical Characteristics and Selected Laboratory Abnormalities of 111 Patients Infected with H7N9 Virus *</figDesc><figDesc>The New England Journal of Medicine Downloaded from nejm.org on May 22, 2013. For personal use only. No other uses without permission. Copyright &#169; 2013 Massachusetts Medical Society. All rights reserved.</figDesc><figDesc>Complications, Treatment, and Clinical Outcomes in 111 Patients Infected with H7N9 Virus.*</figDesc><figDesc>Multivariate Analysis of Risk Factors for the 79 Patients with the Acute Respiratory Distress Syndrome.</figDesc></body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div />
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div><p>Clinical Findings in H7N9 Virus Infection n engl j med nejm.org </p><p>We thank the National Health and Family Planning Commission of China for coordinating data collection and analysis; Prof. Chen Wang of Beijing Hospital, Ministry of Health, for his advice regarding the clinical study, data analysis, and preparation of the manuscript; and Dr. Hui Li of Beijing Chao-Yang Hospital, Capital Medical University, and Drs. Xia Hong Dai and Shi Gui Yang of Zhejiang University for their help in data collection and statistical analysis.</p></div>
<div><head>Appendix</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human infection with a novel avian-origin influenza A (H7N9) virus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Hu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">368</biblScope>
			<biblScope from="1888" to="97" unit="page" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human infections with the emerging avian influenza A H7N9 virus from wet market poultry: clinical analysis and characterisation of viral genome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Y</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013-04-25" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Epub ahead of print</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Global concerns regarding novel influenza A (H7N9) virus infections</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Uyeki</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Cox</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">368</biblScope>
			<biblScope from="1862" to="1867" unit="page" />
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Number of confirmed human cases of avian influenza A(H7N9) reported to WHO. Geneva: World Health Organization</title>
		<ptr target="http://www.who.int/influenza/human_animal_interface/influenza_h7n9/05_Report-WebH7N9Number.pdf" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013-05" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Preliminary report: epidemiology of the avian influenza A (H7N9) outbreak in China</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>DOI: 10.1056/ NEJMoa1304617</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2013" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Influenza-associated hospitalizations in the United States</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Thompson</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Shay</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">E</forename><surname>Weintraub</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">JAMA</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">292</biblScope>
			<biblScope from="1333" to="1373" unit="page" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Antiviral therapy and outcomes of patients with pneumonia caused by influenza A pandemic (H1N1) virus</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">G</forename><surname>Yang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">B</forename><surname>Bin Cao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Liang</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">7</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">29652</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2012" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinical characteristics of 26 human cases of highly pathogenic avian influenza A (H5N1) virus infection in China</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Yu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Gao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Z</forename><surname>Feng</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">PLoS One</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">8</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page">2985</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2008" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Severe human influenza infections in Thailand: oseltamivir treatment and risk factors for fatal outcome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Hanshaoworakul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Simmerman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">U</forename><surname>Narueponjirakul</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno>e6051. 10</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">China. Chest</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope from="1156" to="64" unit="page" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PLoS One</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinical features of human influenza A (H5N1) infection in Vietnam</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Liem</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">V</forename><surname>Tung</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Hien</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Clin Infect Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope from="1639" to="1685" unit="page" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Antiviral therapy and outcomes of influenza requiring hospitalization in Ontario</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Mcgeer</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Green</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Plevneshi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Canada. Clin Infect Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">45</biblScope>
			<biblScope from="1568" to="75" unit="page" />
			<date type="published" when="2007" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Avian influenza virus infections in humans</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Ssy</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Yuen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Chest</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">129</biblScope>
			<biblScope from="156" to="68" unit="page" />
			<date type="published" when="2006" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Past, present, and possible future human infection with influenza virus A subtype H7</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Belser</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">B</forename><surname>Bridges</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Katz</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Tumpey</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Emerg Infect Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">15</biblScope>
			<biblScope from="859" to="65" unit="page" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The Writing Committee of the World Health Organization (WHO) Consultation on Human Influenza A/H5. Avian influenza A (H5N1) infection in humans</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">353</biblScope>
			<biblScope from="1374" to="85" unit="page" />
			<date type="published" when="2005" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Melting muscles: novel H1N1 influenza A associated rhabdomyolysis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D&amp;apos;</forename><surname>Silva</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><surname>Hewagama</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Doherty</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Korman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Buttery</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Pediatr Infect Dis J</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">28</biblScope>
			<biblScope from="1138" to="1147" unit="page" />
			<date type="published" when="2009" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human disease from influenza A (H5N1)</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Chotpitayasunondh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><surname>Ungchusak</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Hanshaoworakul</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Emerg Infect Dis</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">11</biblScope>
			<biblScope from="201" to="210" unit="page" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Avian influenza A (H5N1) in 10 patients in Vietnam</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">H</forename><surname>Tran</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Nguyen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Nguyen</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">350</biblScope>
			<biblScope from="1179" to="88" unit="page" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Clinical management of human infection with pandemic (H1N1) 2009: revised</title>
		<imprint />
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>