<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/abel/Downloads/grobid-0.5.6/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd" xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Comment</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher />
				<availability status="unknown"><licence /></availability>
				<date>395 March 7, 2020</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author role="corresp">
							<persName><forename type="first">Jie</forename><surname>Qiao</surname></persName>
							<email>jie.qiao@263.net</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName key="dep1" type="department">Center for Reproductive Medicine</orgName>
								<orgName key="dep2" type="department">Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology</orgName>
								<orgName key="dep3" type="department">National Clinical Research Center for Obstetrics and Gynecology</orgName>
								<orgName key="dep4" type="department">Ministry of Education</orgName>
								<orgName type="laboratory">Key Laboratory of Assisted Reproduction (Peking University)</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Peking University Third Hospital</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100191, 100191, 100191</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing, Beijing, Beijing</settlement>
									<country>China, China, China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="laboratory">Beijing Key Laboratory of Reproductive Endocrinology and Assisted Reproductive Technology</orgName>
								<address>
									<postCode>100191</postCode>
									<settlement>Beijing</settlement>
									<country key="CN">China</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Comment</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">www.thelancet.com</title>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published">395 March 7, 2020</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<note>760 The Chinese version of this Comment is provided in the appendix. I declare no competing interests.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>

		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application ident="GROBID" version="0.5.6" when="2020-03-16T22:29+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>		<profileDesc>
			<abstract />
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div><p>Since December, 2019, the outbreak of the 2019 novel coronavirus disease (COVID19) infection has become a major epidemic threat in China. As of </p><p>As the COVID19 outbreak unfolds, prevention and control of COVID19 infection among pregnant women and the potential risk of vertical transmission have become a major concern. More evidence is needed to develop effective preventive and clinical strategies. The latest research by Huijun Chen and colleagues 5 reported in The Lancet provides some insight into the clinical characteristics, pregnancy outcomes, and vertical transmission potential of COVID19 infection in pregnant women. Although the study analysed only a small number of cases (nine women with confirmed COVID19 pneumonia), under such emergent circum stances these findings are valuable for preventive and clinical practice in China and elsewhere. Although neonatal nasopharyngeal swab samples have been collected in some hospitals across China, this study also collected and tested amniotic fluid, cord blood, and breastmilk samples for the presence of severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARSCoV2), thus allowing a more detailed assessment of the vertical transmission potential of COVID19 infection.</p><p>SARSCoV2 is a new strain of coronaviruses that are pathogenic to humans. Another two notable strains are SARSCoV and the Middle East respiratory syndrome (MERS) coronavirus (MERSCoV). A study done by Roujian Lu and colleagues 6 found that although SARSCoV2 is genetically closer to two batderived SARSlike coronaviruses, batSLCoVZC45 and bat SLCoVZXC21 (with about 88% genome sequence identity), than to SARSCoV1 (about 79% identity) and MERSCoV (about 50% identity), homology modelling has revealed that SARSCoV2 has a similar receptor binding domain structure to that of SARSCoV1, which suggests that COVID19 infection might have a similar pathogenesis to SARSCoV1 infection. </p><p>We declare no competing interests.</p><p>Stephanie colleagues did not find any evidence of the presence of SARSCoV2 viral particles in the products of conception or in neonates, in accordance with the findings of a previous study on SARSCoV1 done by Wong and colleagues. </p><p>We need to further strengthen our capacity to deal with emergent infectious disease outbreaks, through laws and regulations to prevent and control the spread of infectious diseases and to avoid outbreak clusters in families, communities, and other public places, and to do so with transparency and solidarity. Timely reporting and disclosure of emergent infectious diseases is also important to avoid delayed responses. Infection control and management procedures in hospitals and other places with several confirmed cases isolated together should also be maintained, and specialised clothing and equipment provided to protect medical professionals and other health workers from occupational exposure to COVID19 infection. The number of people with novel coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID19) has risen above 75 000 globally, over 99% of whom are in China, with more than 900 cases in 25 other countries as of Feb 20, 2020. 1,2 Science, however, is stepping up to the challenge. Consider the example of Africa's efforts to scale up its capacity to detect any cases of infection. On Feb 3, 2020, the only African countries with laboratories that could test for severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARSCoV2) were South Africa and Senegal. This scarce capacity was a major concern for a continent bracing for possible infections. Just a fortnight later, WHO had sent testing kits to 27 countries on the continent, which are already being used. 3 By the end of this week, the number of countries able to detect COVID19 is expected to have risen to 40. The Africa Centres for Disease Control and Prevention has led training for these countries in Senegal, with further sessions scheduled for the week of Feb 24, 2020, in South Africa. </p><p>Fortunately, scientists around the world are working at breakneck speed to figure out how to detect, treat, and control the new coronavirus. On Feb 10-12, 2020, WHO brought almost 400 scientists together for a research and innovation forum on the new coronavirus. </p><p>The roadmap is intended to enable scientists, researchers, and funders to coordinate and align</p></div>
<div><head>Scientists are sprinting to outpace the novel coronavirus</head><p>Published Online February 20, 2020 https://doi.org/10.1016/ S01406736(20)304207</p></div><figDesc>H Read, *Sarah H Wild sarah.wild@ed.ac.uk Donnell MJ, Chin SL, Rangarajan S, et al. Global and regional effects of potentially modifiable risk factors associated with acute stroke in 32 countries (INTERSTROKE): a casecontrol study. Lancet 2016; 388: 761-75. 7 Yusuf S, Hawken S, Ounpuu S, et al. Effect of potentially modifiable risk factors associated with myocardial infarction in 52 countries (the INTERHEART study): casecontrol study. Lancet 2004; 364: 937-52. 8 Olsen MH, Angell SY, Asma S, et al. A call to action and a lifecourse strategy to address the global burden of raised blood pressure on current and future generations: the Lancet Commission on hypertension. Lancet 2016; 388: 2665-712. 9 Appelman Y, van Rijn BB, Ten Haaf ME, Boersma E, Peters SA. Sex differences in cardiovascular risk factors and disease prevention. Atherosclerosis 2015; 241: 211-18.</figDesc></body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">4 National Health Commission of the People's Republic of China. Notice of the General Office of the National Health and Health Commission on issuing a new coronavirus pneumonia prevention and control plan</title>
		<ptr target="http://www.nhc.gov.cn/xcs/zhengcwj/202002/573340613ab243b3a7f61df260551dd4.shtml" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020-02-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>4th edition</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinical characteristics and intrauterine vertical transmission potential of COVID19 infection in nine pregnant women: a retrospective review of medical records</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Guo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S01406736(20)303603</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/S01406736(20)303603" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020-02-12" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published online</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Genomic characterisation and epidemiology of 2019 novel coronavirus: implications for virus origins and receptor binding</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Lu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Zhao</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S01406736(20</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/S01406736(20" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">302518</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2020-01-30" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published online</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Tissue distribution of ACE2 protein, the functional receptor for SARS coronavirus. A first step in understanding SARS pathogenesis</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">I</forename><surname>Hamming</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">W</forename><surname>Timens</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Mlc</forename><surname>Bulthuis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">T</forename><surname>Lely</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">J</forename><surname>Navis</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Van Goor</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Pathol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">203</biblScope>
			<biblScope from="631" to="668" unit="page" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Exploring the pathogenesis of severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS): the tissue distribution of the coronavirus (SARSCoV) and its putative receptor</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>To</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">W</forename><surname>Lo</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint />
	</monogr>
	<note>angiotensinconverting enzyme 2 (ACE2)</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J Pathol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">203</biblScope>
			<biblScope from="740" to="783" unit="page" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pregnancy and perinatal outcomes of women with severe acute respiratory syndrome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">K</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Chow</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Leung</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Am J Obstet Gynecol</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">191</biblScope>
			<biblScope from="292" to="97" unit="page" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">National Health Commission of the People's Republic of China</title>
		<ptr target="http://www.nhc.gov.cn/xcs/s3574/202002/5bc099fc9144445297e8776838e57ddc.shtml" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Transcript of Press Conference on Feb</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020-02-07" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">A casecontrolled study comparing clinical course and outcomes of pregnant and nonpregnant women with severe acute respiratory syndrome</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Lam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">F</forename><surname>Wong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><forename type="middle">N</forename><surname>Leung</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">BJOG</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">111</biblScope>
			<biblScope from="771" to="74" unit="page" />
			<date type="published" when="2004" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Clinical analysis of 10 neonates born to mothers with 2019nCoV pneumonia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Zhu</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">L</forename><surname>Wang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">C</forename><surname>Fang</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.21037/tp.2020.02.06</idno>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Transl Pediatr</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020-02-10" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published online</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Epidemiological and clinical characteristics of 99 cases of 2019 novel coronavirus pneumonia in Wuhan, China: a descriptive study</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">N</forename><surname>Chen</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Zhou</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Dong</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<idno type="DOI">10.1016/S01406736(20)302117</idno>
		<ptr target="https://doi.org/10.1016/S01406736(20)302117" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Lancet</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020-01-30" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>published online</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Early transmission dynamics in Wuhan, China, of novel coronavirusinfected pneumonia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Q</forename><surname>Li</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">X</forename><surname>Guan</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><surname>Wu</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">N Engl J Med</title>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">National Health Commission of the People's Republic of China. Notice on strengthening maternal disease treatment and safe midwifery during the prevention and control of new coronavirus pneumonia</title>
		<ptr target="http://www.nhc.gov.cn/xcs/zhengcwj/202002/4f80657b346e4d6ba76e2cfc3888c630.shtml" />
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2020-02-08" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>