<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 /home/abel/Downloads/grobid-0.5.6/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
				<date type="published" when="2020-03">March 2020</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date type="published" when="2020-03">March 2020</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="DOI">10.13140/RG.2.2.15338.67526</idno>
					<note>See discussions, stats, and author profiles for this publication at: https://www.researchgate.net/publication/339875297 1 author: Some of the authors of this publication are also working on these related projects: Emerging Infectious Diseases View project Molecular etiology of squamous cell carcinoma of esophagus in a high-risk population from Kashmir View project S A Tabish Sher-i-Kashmir Institute of Medical Sciences 401 PUBLICATIONS 813 CITATIONS SEE PROFILE All content following this page was uploaded by S A Tabish on 12 March 2020. The user has requested enhancement of the downloaded file.</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>

		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.5.6" ident="GROBID" when="2020-03-16T22:29+0000">
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RESPONDING TO THE CHALLENGE OF CORONAVIRUS (2019-nCoV) PANDEMIC</head><p>A new respiratory coronavirus, 2019-nCoV, is rapidly spreading throughout world. So far, over 126,515 cases have been diagnosed globally with 4637 deaths. Infections have been reported by 124 countries. 68317 patients have recovered. Currently, the epidemic areas cover mainland China, Iran, South Korea, Italy, the ski resorts in Tyrol in Austria, and the state of North Rhine-Westphalia in Germany. Canada has recorded its first death from the new coronavirus.</p><p>The COVID-19 viral disease that has swept into at least 114 countries and killed more than 4,000 people is now officially a pandemic, the World Health Organization announced Wednesday. "This is the first pandemic caused by coronavirus," WHO Director-General Tedros declared at a briefing in Geneva. It's the first time the WHO has called an outbreak a pandemic since the H1N1 "swine flu" in 2009. Even as he raised the health emergency to its highest level, Tedros said hope remains that COVID-19 can be curtailed. And he urged countries to take action now to stop the disease. "WHO has been in full response mode since we were notified of the first cases," And we have called every day for countries to take urgent and aggressive action. We have rung the alarm bell loud and clear. It's now up to other countries to prove they can stop the disease'.</p><p>"The challenge for many countries who are now dealing with large clusters or community transmission is not whether they can do the same," he said. "It's whether they will."</p><p>The human race is locked in a battle against something five million times smaller than us. The novel coronavirus has gone from an unknown enemy to feared worldwide, in a matter of months.</p><p>The first cases likely occurred in people who had close contact with infected animals. Most new cases from this 2019-nCoV are being passed human to human. It certainly is being maintained by human transmission.</p><p>The number of people infected by the new coronavirus surpassed 100,000 globally, according to a tally by Reuters news agency based on statements from health ministries and government officials across the world, with at least 3,015 deaths in China and 267 deaths across the globe, many in Italy and Iran. WHO Director General, Dr. Tedros warned that time to contain the virus was running out. "Now is the time to act," he said. The coronavirus COVID-19 is affecting 124 countries and territories around the world and 1 international conveyance (the Diamond Princess cruise ship harbored in Yokohama, Japan). There have been 80,796 Total Cases in China, 12462 in Italy, 9000 in Iran, 7889 in S. <ref type="bibr">Korea, 2281</ref><ref type="bibr">in France, 2277</ref><ref type="bibr">in Spain, 1966</ref><ref type="bibr">in Germany, 1336</ref> in Singapore, India 73.</p><p>Coronaviruses are enveloped non-segmented positive-sense RNA viruses belonging to the family Coronaviridae and the order Nidovirales and broadly distributed in humans and other mammals. Coronaviruses typically target the upper respiratory tract, causing a range of illnesses which can potentially include pneumonia. But there is growing evidence they can move further down the body, and also affect the central nervous system, causing long-term neurological damage.</p><p>Although most human coronavirus infections are mild, the epidemics of the two betacoronaviruses, severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV) and Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV), have caused more than 10 000 cumulative cases in the past two decades, with mortality rates of 10% for SARS-CoV and 37% for MERS-CoV. Human coronaviruses, including hCoV-229E, OC43, NL63, and HKU1, cause mild respiratory diseases. Fatal coronavirus infections that have emerged in the past two decades are severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV) and the Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus The disease has a fatality rate of less than 2 percent-exponentially lower than most outbreaks that make global news. The virus has raised alarm not despite that low fatality rate, but because of it.</p><p>Coronaviruses are similar to influenza viruses in that they both contain single strands of RNA. Four coronaviruses commonly infect humans, causing colds. These are believed to have evolved in humans to maximize their own spread-which means sickening, but not killing, people. By contrast, the two prior novel coronavirus outbreaks-SARS (severe acute respiratory syndrome) and MERS (Middle East respiratory syndrome, named for where the first outbreak occurred)-were picked up from animals, as was H5N1. These diseases were highly fatal to humans. COVID-19 is deadly, but not too deadly. It makes people sick, but not in predictable, uniquely identifiable ways.</p><p>The world has responded with unprecedented speed and mobilization of resources. The new virus was identified extremely quickly. Its genome was sequenced by Chinese scientists and shared around the world within weeks. The global scientific community has shared genomic and clinical data at unprecedented rates. Work on a vaccine is well under way.</p><p>Super spreaders shed far larger numbers of the virus particles than other patients, increasing the chance they will infect someone else.</p><p>While health systems in high-income countries would be stretched by the outbreak, the most devastating effects would be in countries with weak health systems, ongoing conflicts, or existing infectious disease epidemics. In these countries, it is imperative to rapidly detect and contain the virus at points of entry to prevent community transmission and health systems from being overwhelmed.</p><p>Several potential treatments have been proposed, including a Janus kinase inibitor known as baricitinib. However, no antiviral treatment has been approved for coronaviruses, and despite two outbreaks of novel coronaviruses in the past two decades, vaccine development is still in its infancy. WHO has announced that a vaccine for SARS-CoV-2 should be available in 18 months.</p><p>With the increasing frequency of zoonotic spill overs leading to human infections and transmission, it's apparent that pandemic preparedness has become a priority for the global health agenda.</p><p>Those who screen positive should be isolated and treated until tested and, if positive, quarantined until they are no longer capable of transmitting infection.</p><p>Asymptomatic transmission (transmitting the disease by someone who displays no symptoms) is possible, all contacts and people who have been exposed to areas with known transmission would also need to be tested, regardless of whether they show any signs of illness.</p><p>Since virtually anyone living in an area of transmission could have been exposed, any of the thousands who develop a fever or a cough each day need to be isolated and treated while awaiting laboratory testing.</p><p>A system could immediately be established to take test samples from patients with concerning symptoms who are not severely ill and then send them home with protective respirator masks, instructions on hand-washing to prevent the further spread of the disease, and orders to remain at home until the test results come back. If hospital beds are still limited, patients found to be positive who aren't severely ill could remain isolated and be treated at home and be only hospitalized if their condition worsens. This approach could preserve precious hospital capacity for those who need it most and prevent people who turn out not to have the disease from being infected in hospitals while awaiting laboratory results.</p><p>The development of rapid, "point-of-care" diagnostic tests is critical for tackling 2019-nCoV that could be developed and manufactured for use. Similar to the way U.S. hospitals use rapid-screening swabs during flu season, these tests could be widely used at hospitals, checkpoints, and even households to screen anyone who develops suspicious symptoms or, if asymptomatic transmission proves possible, used to test every person every few weeks to ensure no one is unknowingly spreading the virus. Those screened positive should still undergo laboratory testing for confirmation.</p><p>The 2019-nCoV epidemic is evolving by the hour. We need to move swiftly to respond to this threat. 2019-nCoV caused clusters of fatal pneumonia with clinical presentation greatly resembling SARS-CoV. Patients infected with 2019-nCoV might develop acute respiratory distress syndrome, have a high likelihood of admission to intensive care, and might die. The cytokine storm could be associated with disease severity.</p><p>We have yet to find an effective vaccine or cure for it. The speed at which coronaviruses mutate and so change their characteristics makes them hard to vaccinate against. Even if it can be diagnosed quickly, finding an effective treatment for a virus like this is famously difficult. These long-term government investments matter because creating vaccines, antiviral medications, and other vital tools requires decades of serious investment, even when demand is low. There is an urgent need to develop effective diagnostics, therapeutics, and vaccines.</p><p>As per WHO, severe and mounting disruption to the global supply of personal protective equipment (PPE) -caused by rising demand, panic buying, hoarding and misuse -is putting lives at risk from the new coronavirus and other infectious diseases.</p><p>Asian Development Bank says economic losses could reach $347bn as more than 100,000 people are diagnosed with disease. In a world of 7.7 billion people, countries have to be in a state of emergency preparedness to tackle emerging infectious diseases. It needs aggressive and focused action: coordinating every part of government -health, security, diplomacy, finance, commerce, transport, trade, information, etc.</p><p>Prof. S. A. Tabish Srinagar amintabish@gmail.com</p></div>		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
